In half a century of trying to help prevent wars,
طوال نصف قرن قضيتها محاولة المساعدة في منع الحروب
there's one question that never leaves me:
كان هناك سؤالاً واحداً لا يغادرني
How do we deal with extreme violence
كيف نتعامل مع العنف الشديد
without using force in return?
دون الحاجة إلى إستخدام القوة في المقابل؟
When you're faced with brutality,
عندما يتم مواجهتك بالوحشية
whether it's a child facing a bully on a playground
سواء كان طفلاِ يواجهه بلطجي في مكان اللعب
or domestic violence --
أو كان عنفاً منزلياً
or, on the streets of Syria today,
أو كان في شوارع سوريا هذه الأيام
facing tanks and shrapnel,
في مواجهة الدبابات و الشظايا
what's the most effective thing to do?
ما هو ألشيء الأكثر فاعلية الذي يمكن القيام به؟
Fight back? Give in?
المقاومة؟ الإستسلام؟
Use more force?
إستخدام المزيد من القوة؟
This question: "How do I deal with a bully
هذا السؤال: "كيف أتعامل مع البلطجي
without becoming a thug in return?"
دون أن أصبح بلطجياً"؟
has been with me ever since I was a child.
كان يشغلني منذ الطفولة
I remember I was about 13,
في الثالثة عشر من عمري اذكر أني
glued to a grainy black and white television in my parents' living room
كنت متسمرة أمام التلفاز القديم في غرفة المعيشة مع والدي
as Soviet tanks rolled into Budapest,
أشاهد دبابات الاتحاد السوفييتي تغزو بودابست
and kids not much older than me
بينما أطفال قريبون من عمري
were throwing themselves at the tanks
يلقون بأنفسهم في طريق الدبابات
and getting mown down.
و يتم دهسهم.
And I rushed upstairs and started packing my suitcase.
وقتها هرعت إلى غرفتي بالأعلى وبدأت بحزم أمتعتي
And my mother came up and said, "What on Earth are you doing?"
لحقت بي أمي وسألت مستنكرة: "مالذي تحاولين فعله؟"
And I said, "I'm going to Budapest."
أجبت: "أنا ذاهبة إلى بودابست"
And she said, "What on Earth for?"
فأردفت قائلة: "لماذا؟"
And I said, "Kids are getting killed there.
أجبتها: "الأطفال يُقتلون هناك،
There's something terrible happening."
أشياء فظيعة تحدث هناك."
And she said, "Don't be so silly."
فردت علي: "لا تكوني سخيفة."
And I started to cry.
حينها بدأت أنا بالبكاء
And she got it, she said,
عندها بدأت تتفهم وقالت:
"Okay, I see it's serious.
"حسنا، الأمر جدي على ما يبدو.
You're much too young to help.
أنت مازلت صغيرة في السن
You need training. I'll help you.
أنت بحاجة إلى التدريب، وأنا سأساعدك.
But just unpack your suitcase."
لكن كفي عن حزم أمتعتك.
And so I got some training
وبهذا، بدأ التدريب.
and went and worked in Africa during most of my 20s.
ذهبت و عملت في افريقيا لمعظم العقد الثاني من عمري
But I realized that what I really needed to know
لكني أدركت أنه ماكان يتوجب علي معرفته
I couldn't get from training courses.
ليس من الممكن الحصول عليه من برامج التدريب
I wanted to understand
أردت أن افهم
how violence, how oppression, works.
الكيفية التي يتم بها الظلم و الاضطهاد
And what I've discovered since is this:
وما اتضح لي منذ ذلك الحين هو:
Bullies use violence in three ways.
المعتدون يوظفون العنف بثلاث طرق
They use political violence to intimidate,
يستخدمون العنف السياسي لتطويع الآخرين بالقوة
physical violence to terrorize
و العنف الجسدي لإثارة الذعر
and mental or emotional violence to undermine.
و العنف النفسي أو العقلي للتقويض
And only very rarely in very few cases
ونادراً جداً في حالات قليلة
does it work to use more violence.
ينجح استخدام عنف أكثر.
Nelson Mandela went to jail believing in violence,
نيلسون مانديلا ذهب للسجن معتقداً بالعنف،
and 27 years later
وبعد 27 سنة
he and his colleagues
هو و زملاءه
had slowly and carefully
كانوا ببطء وحذر
honed the skills, the incredible skills, that they needed
شحذوا مهارات، مهارات رائعة، احتاجوها
to turn one of the most vicious governments the world has known
ليحولوا حكومة من أبشع الحكومات المعروفة
into a democracy.
إلى ديموقراطية
And they did it in a total devotion to non-violence.
و فعلوا ذلك بتكريس كامل لعدم العنف.
They realized that using force against force
أدركوا أن استعمال القوة ضد القوة
doesn't work.
لا ينفع.
So what does work?
لذا مالذي ينفع؟
Over time I've collected about a half-dozen methods
مع مرور الزمن جمعت حوالي نصف دزينة من الطرق
that do work -- of course there are many more --
التي تعمل وتنفع -- بالطبع يوجد العديد منها
that do work and that are effective.
طرق تعمل وفعالة .
And the first is
و الأولى هي
that the change that has to take place
أن التغير الذي يجب أن يحدث
has to take place here, inside me.
يجب أن يحدث هنا، داخلي.
It's my response, my attitude, to oppression
إنها إستجابتي، طريقتي، سلوكي، مع الطاغي
that I've got control over,
هو الشيء الذي أملك السيطرة عليه
and that I can do something about.
وهو الشيء الذي أستطيع فعل شيئ تجاهه.
And what I need to develop is self-knowledge to do that.
وما أحتاجه لتطوير معرفتي لفعل ذلك.
That means I need to know how I tick,
ذلك يعني أني أحتاج لأعرف كيف أشير
when I collapse,
عندما أنهار،
where my formidable points are,
أين نقاط قوتي الهائلة،
where my weaker points are.
و أين نقاط ضعفي.
When do I give in?
متى أستسلم؟
What will I stand up for?
ماهو الشيء الذي سأقف لأجله ؟
And meditation or self-inspection
والاستبصار أو إستكشاف-النفس
is one of the ways -- again it's not the only one --
هي واحدة من الطرق -- مرة أخرى ليست الوحيدة --
it's one of the ways
هي واحدة من طرق
of gaining this kind of inner power.
كسب ذلك النوع من القوة الداخلية.
And my heroine here -- like Satish's --
و هيرويني هنا -- مثل ساتيش
is Aung San Suu Kyi in Burma.
هو أونق سان سو تشي في بورما.
She was leading a group of students
كانت قائدة لمجموعة من الطلاب
on a protest in the streets of Rangoon.
في مظاهرة في شوارع رانجون.
They came around a corner faced with a row of machine guns.
جاؤا حول زاوية مواجهين أسلحة و مسدسات.
And she realized straight away
و أدركت في اللحظة
that the soldiers with their fingers shaking on the triggers
أن الجنود مع أصابعهم ترجف على الزناد
were more scared than the student protesters behind her.
كانوا أكثر خوفاً من الطلاب المتظاهرين خلفها.
But she told the students to sit down.
لكنها أخبرت الطلاب أن يجلسوا
And she walked forward with such calm and such clarity
ومشت متقدمة للأمام بهدوء و وضوح
and such total lack of fear
و بمشاعر خالية من الخوف
that she could walk right up to the first gun,
مشت إلى أول مسدس
put her hand on it and lower it.
وضعت يدها عليه و أنزلته.
And no one got killed.
ولم يقتل أحد.
So that's what the mastery of fear can do --
لذا هذا ما يستطيع فعله التحكم بالخوف
not only faced with machine guns,
ليس فقط مواجهة الأسلحة،
but if you meet a knife fight in the street.
لكن إذا صادفت مشاجرة سكاكين في الطريق.
But we have to practice.
لكن علينا أن نتمرن.
So what about our fear?
ماذا عن خوفنا؟
I have a little mantra.
لدي تعويذة صغيرة
My fear grows fat
خوفي يزداد سمنة
on the energy I feed it.
بالطاقة التي أطعمه.
And if it grows very big
و عندما ينمو بشكل كبير
it probably happens.
فإنه ربما يحدث.
So we all know the three o'clock in the morning syndrome,
إذا جميعنا يعرف متناذرة الساعة الثالثة صباحاً،
when something you've been worrying about wakes you up --
عندما يوقظك شيئاً ما كنت قلقاً بشأنه --
I see a lot of people --
أرى العديد من الأشخاص
and for an hour you toss and turn,
ولمدة ساعة تتقلب من جانب لجانب،
it gets worse and worse,
و تسوء الحالة أكثر و أكثر
and by four o'clock you're pinned to the pillow
حتى الساعة الرابعة تصبح مدبس بالمخدة
by a monster this big.
من قبل وحش بهذا الكبر
The only thing to do
والأمر الوحيد الذي تستطيع فعله
is to get up, make a cup of tea
هو أن تقوم، وتصنع لنفسك كوب من الشاي
and sit down with the fear like a child beside you.
وتجلس بجانب الخوف كأنه طفل صغير
You're the adult.
أنت شخص راشد
The fear is the child.
الخوف هو الطفل
And you talk to the fear
وتتحدث مع الخوف
and you ask it what it wants, what it needs.
وتسأله ماذا يريد، ماذا يحتاج.
How can this be made better?
كيف تستطيع جعله الأمور أفضل؟
How can the child feel stronger?
كيف يستطيع الطفل أن يشعر أنه أقوى؟
And you make a plan.
وتصنع خطة.
And you say, "Okay, now we're going back to sleep.
وتقول، " حسناً، الآن سنعود للنوم
Half-past seven, we're getting up and that's what we're going to do."
بعد السابعة النصف، سنستيقظ وذلك ما سنفعله"
I had one of these 3 a.m. episodes on Sunday --
حصلت لي واحدة من تلك المتناذرات " متناذرة الثالثة صباحاً" في يوم الأحد
paralyzed with fear at coming to talk to you.
مشلولة مع الخوف من القدوم للحديث.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I did the thing.
لذا فعلت ذلك الشيء.
I got up, made the cup of tea, sat down with it, did it all
قمت، عملت كوب من الشاي، جلست مع الخوف، فعلت كل ذلك.
and I'm here -- still partly paralyzed, but I'm here.
و أنا هنا -- مع ذلك لازلت بطريقة جزئية مشلولة، لكني هنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So that's fear. What about anger?
إذاً ذلك الخوف. ماذا عن الغضب؟
Wherever there is injustice there's anger.
أينما وجد الظلم وجد الغضب.
But anger is like gasoline,
لكن الغضب مثل غازولين،
and if you spray it around and somebody lights a match,
لو رششته في الأنحاء و شخص ما أشعل عود الثقاب،
you've got an inferno.
أوجدت جحيم.
But anger as an engine -- in an engine -- is powerful.
لكن الغضب كالمحرّك -- في المحرك -- قوته
If we can put our anger inside an engine,
إذا استطعنا وضع غضبنا في داخل محرّك،
it can drive us forward,
يمكن أن يقودنا للأمام،
it can get us through the dreadful moments
يمكن أن يخرجنا من اللحظات المروعة،
and it can give us real inner power.
ويمكن أن يعطينا قوة داخلية حقيقية.
And I learned this in my work
وتعلمت هذا في عملي
with nuclear weapon policy-makers.
مع معدي- سياسة الأسلحة النووية.
Because at the beginning I was so outraged
لأني في البداية كنت جداً غاضبة
at the dangers they were exposing us to
من الخطر الذي يعرضونا له
that I just wanted to argue and blame and make them wrong.
بحيث أصبحت أريد أن أجادل و ألوم و أجعلهم مخطئين.
Totally ineffective.
غير فعال أبداً.
In order to develop a dialogue for change
ومن أجل تطوير حوار للتغير
we have to deal with our anger.
يجب أن نتعامل مع غضبنا.
It's okay to be angry with the thing --
لابأس أن نكون غاضبين من الشيء --
the nuclear weapons in this case --
في هذه الحالة السلاح النووي --
but it is hopeless to be angry with the people.
لكنه أمر ميئوس منه أن تكون غاضب من الناس.
They are human beings just like us.
هم أشخاص بشريون مثلنا.
And they're doing what they think is best.
وهم يفعلون ما يظنون أنه الافضل.
And that's the basis on which we have to talk with them.
و ذلك الأساس الذي يجب أن نتحدث به معهم.
So that's the third one, anger.
إذا هذا ثالث موضوع، الغضب.
And it brings me to the crux
و يوصلني إلى صلب الموضوع
of what's going on, or what I perceive as going on,
من ما يحدث، أو ما أعي حدوثه،
in the world today,
في العالم اليوم،
which is that last century was top-down power.
وهو القرن الأخير الذي كانت القوة في فيه من الأعلى-للأسفل
It was still governments telling people what to do.
لازالت الحكومات تخبر الناس بما يجب عليهم فعله.
This century there's a shift.
في هذا القرن يوجد تحول.
It's bottom-up or grassroots power.
إنه من الأسفل الى الأعلى أو قوة الشعب.
It's like mushrooms coming through concrete.
إنه مثل فطر يخرج من اسمنت.
It's people joining up with people, as Bundy just said, miles away
إنه الناس تتضامن مع الناس، مثل ما قال بندي، أميال بعيدة
to bring about change.
لإحضار التغيير.
And Peace Direct spotted quite early on
واتجاه سلمي لوحظ مبكراً
that local people in areas of very hot conflict
أن الأشخاص المحليين في مناطق الخلاف الشديد
know what to do.
يعرفون ما يفعلون.
They know best what to do.
يعرفون بشكل أفضل ما يفعلون.
So Peace Direct gets behind them to do that.
لذا اتجاه السلام يصبح خلفهم ليفعل ذلك.
And the kind of thing they're doing
ونوع ما يفعلونه
is demobilizing militias,
تسريح الميليشيات،
rebuilding economies,
إعادة بناء الإقتصاد،
resettling refugees,
إعادة استقلال اللاجئين،
even liberating child soldiers.
حتى تحرير الأطفال المقاتلين.
And they have to risk their lives almost every day
وعليهم أن يخاطروا بحياتهم تقريباً يومياً
to do this.
ليفعلوا هذا
And what they've realized
و ما أدركوه
is that using violence in the situations they operate in
هو أن استخدام العنف في المواقف التي يعملون بها
is not only less humane,
هو ليس فقط لا إنساني،
but it's less effective
لكن أيضاً أقل فعالية
than using methods that connect people with people, that rebuild.
من استخدام الطرق التي تربط الناس بالناس، التي تعيد بناء.
And I think that the U.S. military
و أعتقد أن عسكر الولايات المتحدة
is finally beginning to get this.
أخيراً بدأت تفهم هذا.
Up to now their counter-terrorism policy
حتى الآن سياسة ضد-الإرهاب الخاصة بهم
has been to kill insurgents at almost any cost,
تقتل المتمردين تقريباً بأي ثمن يكلف،
and if civilians get in the way,
و إذا وجد المدنيين في الطريق،
that's written as "collateral damage."
يكتب عن ذلك "أضرار تبعية."
And this is so infuriating and humiliating
وهذا جداً مغيظ و مهين
for the population of Afghanistan,
لسكان أفغانستان،
that it makes the recruitment for al-Qaeda very easy,
ذلك جعل التجنيد لصالح القاعدة جداً سهل،
when people are so disgusted by, for example,
عندما يكون الناس على سبيل المثال مشمئزون من
the burning of the Koran.
إحراق القرآن.
So the training of the troops has to change.
لذا التدريب للفرق يجب أن يتغير
And I think there are signs that it is beginning to change.
و أعتقد أنه يوجد إشارات أنها بدأت بالتغير.
The British military have always been much better at this.
العسكرية البريطانية كانت دائماً أفضل بكثير في هذا.
But there is one magnificent example for them to take their cue from,
لكن يوجد مثال رائع لهم ليأخذا منه ضربتهم،
and that's a brilliant U.S. lieutenant colonel
وهو الملازم الكولونيل الأمريكي
called Chris Hughes.
كريس هوقس.
And he was leading his men down the streets of Najaf --
كان يقود رجاله في شوارع النجف
in Iraq actually --
في العراق --
and suddenly people were pouring out of the houses on either side of the road,
و فجأة أصبح الناس يصبون من المنازل إلى جانبي الطريق،
screaming, yelling, furiously angry,
يصرخون، و ينادون، بغضب شرس
and surrounded these very young troops who were completely terrified,
و حاصروا تلك الفرق الشابة الذين كانوا مذعورين تماماً،
didn't know what was going on, couldn't speak Arabic.
لم يعرفوا ماذا يجري، لا يستطيعون التحدث بالعربية.
And Chris Hughes strode into the middle of the throng
و كريس هوقس خطا بخطوات كبيرة إلى منتصف الحشد
with his weapon above his head, pointing at the ground,
مع سلاحه فوق رأسه مشيراً إلى الأرض،
and he said, "Kneel."
وقال، "اركعوا"
And these huge soldiers
و أولئك الجنود الكثار.
with their backpacks and their body armor,
مع حقائب ظهورهم و أجسامهم المسلحة،
wobbled to the ground.
تمايلوا إلى الأرض
And complete silence fell.
و شعروا بصمت تام.
And after about two minutes,
و بعد مايتجاوز الدقيقتين،
everybody moved aside and went home.
الجميع تحركوا بعيداً و ذهبوا لمنازلهم.
Now that to me is wisdom in action.
الآن بالنسبة لي هذه هي الحكمة في التصرف على الأرض.
In the moment, that's what he did.
في اللحظة، ذلك ما فعله.
And it's happening everywhere now.
و هو يحدث في كل مكان الآن.
You don't believe me?
لا تصدقوني؟
Have you asked yourselves
هل سألتم أنفسكم
why and how so many dictatorships have collapsed
لماذا و كيف سقط العديد من الدكتاتوريين
over the last 30 years?
خلال الثلاثين سنة السابقة؟
Dictatorships in Czechoslovakia, East Germany,
الدكتاتورية في تشيكوسلوفاكيا، شرق ألمانيا،
Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania,
إستونيا، لاتفيا، ليتوانيا
Mali, Madagascar,
مالي، مدغشقر،
Poland, the Philippines,
بولاند، الفلبين،
Serbia, Slovenia, I could go on,
صربيا، سلوفينيا،
and now Tunisia and Egypt.
والآن تونس و مصر.
And this hasn't just happened.
وذلك لم يحدث للتو.
A lot of it is due to a book
الكثير منه حصل بسبب كتاب
written by an 80-year-old man in Boston, Gene Sharp.
كتب من قبل رجل عمره 80 سنة في بوسطن، جين شارب
He wrote a book called "From Dictatorship to Democracy"
كتب كتاب يدعى "من الدكتاتورية إلى الديموقراطية"
with 81 methodologies for non-violent resistance.
مع 81 طريقة للمقاومة السلمية
And it's been translated into 26 languages.
وتم ترجمته إلى 26 لغة.
It's flown around the world.
و هو يدور في أنحاء العالم
And it's being used by young people and older people everywhere,
ويتم استخدامه من قبل الشبان و الكبار في كل مكان،
because it works and it's effective.
لأنه يعمل وفعال.
So this is what gives me hope --
لذا هذا ما يعطيني أمل --
not just hope, this is what makes me feel very positive right now.
ليس فقط الأمل، هذا يجعلني جداً إيجابية الآن.
Because finally human beings are getting it.
لأنه أخيرا البشر بدأوا يفهمون
We're getting practical, doable methodologies
بدأنا بالعمل الفعلي، بمضاعفة الطرق
to answer my question:
لإجابة سؤالي:
How do we deal with a bully without becoming a thug?
كيف نتعامل مع متنمر بدون أن نصبح سفاحين؟
We're using the kind of skills that I've outlined:
نحن نستخدم المهارات التي أوجزناها
inner power -- the development of inner power -- through self-knowledge,
القوة الداخلية -- تطوير القوة الداخلية -- من خلال معرفة النفس
recognizing and working with our fear,
التعرف والعمل مع مخاوفنا،
using anger as a fuel,
استخدام الغضب كبنزين،
cooperating with others,
التعاون مع الآخرين،
banding together with others,
الترابط مع بعضنا البعض،
courage,
الشجاعة،
and most importantly, commitment to active non-violence.
والأهم، الالتزام لنشاط عدم العنف
Now I don't just believe in non-violence.
الآن لا أؤمن فقط بعدم العنف.
I don't have to believe in it.
لا أتطلب أن أؤمن به
I see evidence everywhere of how it works.
أرى الإثبات في كل مكان في كيفية عمله
And I see that we, ordinary people,
و أجد أننا نحن الأشخاص العاديين
can do what Aung San Suu Kyi and Ghandi and Mandela did.
نستطيع أن نفعل ما فعله أونق سان سوتشي، وغاندي، ومانديلا.
We can bring to an end
يمكننا إيجاد نهاية
the bloodiest century that humanity has ever known.
لأكثر القرون ذرفاً للدم عرف على مر البشرية.
And we can organize to overcome oppression
و بإمكاننا أن نتنظم لنتجاوز الطغيان
by opening our hearts
بفتح قلوبنا
as well as strengthening this incredible resolve.
وأيضا تقوية هذا الحل الرائع
And this open-heartedness is exactly what I've experienced
و تلك القلوب المفتوحة هي تماماً ما جربته
in the entire organization of this gathering since I got here yesterday.
في هذه المنظمة لهذا التجمع منذ أتيت هنا بالأمس.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)